...
Why the team, welcome back to the
channel, welcome back to Worth Your
Time, Worth Your Money. Today, we're
going to have a chat about Roomstead.
Now, oh, okay, this game, there might be
a good game in here, maybe, but my
goodness, it's working overtime to stop
me from finding it. And I'm coming out
of the gate swinging. This reminds me
that the idea of UX, user experience, is
not purely chained to UI, user
interface. However, most people probably
don't even know there's two different
terms. Often, UX and UI are intertwined,
at least in examples that are graspable.
UX It is, it's tricky to explain. But
like a basic example, I don't know,
maybe you have the back button's the
same for nine out of 10 menus, but one
other menu, it's inexplicably B instead
of A or something like that. But often,
even in that example, you could almost
argue that may well be an error in the
UI. It's almost like telegraphing
intent. What the developer wants you to
do is not coming across very well. And
this game is a great,
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; tragically, example of just that. And
I'm look, I'm not really quick to throw
around accusations like deception or
intentionally underhanded marketing, but
my eyebrows prick up a little bit when I
look at the trailer for this game, very
action cut together, and very much
focusing on what looks like autonomous
towns and cities. A lot of the sales
pitch seems to make you think that what
you're seeing in the trailer is what
you'll get in the game, and it's not so.
The citizenry component to this is very
basic. However, after grinding for hours
with this, it's looking like there might
be more involved colony management
mechanics. However, it is so gated
behind grinding bosses and upgrading and
all that. I'm only just glimpsing
[music]
it now. Anyway, a little scathing, but
I'm here to be honest. And just to
finish that point actually on, you know,
all the moving parts going on in the
trailer, I may even have to put b-roll
up of it. They're players. All the guys
moving around doing stuff, picking up
logs and placing them down, they're
players. This game is one to eight
players for sure. I am playing it solo.
I understand that as well. Playing
Valheim solo is a very different example
from playing it with eight mates. So, to
some extent, take what I'm saying with a
grain of salt. But, if you are looking
at the trailer and thinking, "Oh, wow,
look all the little meeples are doing
their own things." That's not That's not
what this is. It's very basic. And last
little caveat, I'm not necessarily into
these
I don't know colony builder games that
are a bit more in that Terraria and
Necesse is a good example. You can check
my old video where I humbly submit that
that is a good game. It's just not
necessarily for me. So, I'm not set
against the genre, but I still recognize
that it might not be my thing. This is
different. This is difficult to enjoy
even if you do like the genre. So, use
that as a touchstone for me in this
space. Okay, but saying that, there is a
lot in common with this like Necesse.
Again, I feel like a lot of that stuff
is derived from Terraria, even Stardew
Valley to a certain point, you know, you
have that top-down pixel art. There is a
charm to it. It looks very pretty. It
This game is very pretty, no doubt about
it. And the setting is kind of novel.
Rome has fallen in the wake of what
seems to be like a zombie apocalypse
incursion. They come out at night. It's
huge pain in the bum because as far as I
can tell you can't time skip night time.
And if you're trying to fight a boss,
you can't really fight at at night time
cuz zombies keep wandering in and
harassing you and third partying you.
So, you have to kind of just sit in town
and wait. But, you know, it's an
interesting idea. You're trying to
rebuild something in a Rome thematic
setting with zombies. You spawn in your
character, you spawn in the world, you
you get skills for doing things. So,
your starting character can have a novel
bonus like plus five melee or something
like that, but it doesn't really matter
in the scheme of anything. [music] At
first, some of the ways that you
interface and interact with the world
seem novel and interesting, but then
they quickly lose their luster and then
they become kind of more fiddly than
necessary. Example, when you uh you
know, you hit things and chop down
trees, they it breaks down into little
log chunks that you can only carry one
at a time. You pick it up and move it
across or you can pick it up and put it
back on the stump of the tree and then
attack it again to turn it into wood
planks. But as the game goes on, you
start to think, "What? Just let me put
the bloody logs in my inventory or
something like that, you know?" I'm
building yet another building and
they're only requiring more stuff as I
go up. I'm going to need four logs,
which means I'm going to have to run out
and carry each one manually back to the
work site, you know? Picking up and
throwing was novel. Probably the most
egregious thing is that if you want to
get sticks, you have to pick up rocks or
whatever and throw them against trees to
knock the sticks out. And when you're
trying to build a hundred arrows because
arrows do like bloody no damage and
you're going to need it to cheese the
boss, it gets old. It gets old throwing
rocks against a tree on infinite items,
especially when the rock bounces off
wherever it wants to go. And you kind of
crap shooting whether you're going to
end up in some sort of rhythm where you
can keep picking the rock up and
throwing it without moving. And look,
there are some technologies that come
along like a like a cart that you can
use to carry logs around. You can put
multiple logs in it at a time, but
again, these things start to grind you
when playing the game becomes
unpleasant. I don't mind novelty in
mechanics. I think it's a great way to
distinguish your game, but if you're
adding things that are slowing the
player down and frustrating them,
especially at the core of it, it's all
about the grind. This is a grind game,
of course it is. Adding extra hurdles
for me to jump is just going to
infuriate me, no matter how cute the
animation or what have it is. Anyway,
let me recenter for a moment. The
citizenry component as I was critical
of, big part of what even got me in the
door in the first place. You essentially
build workplaces, a lumberjack, you
place it down, you have trees nearby,
you can probably plant trees. I'm
picking up seeds and all that, but they
seem to, I don't know, dictate the
income. You do doesn't chop down trees.
I watched him for a little bit, he just
seems to sit in the bloody house, comes
out to get food occasionally, wanders
around. They generate logs. Now, I could
be wrong, but that seems to be it. They
generate the resource. They don't pick
up things, they don't move around, they
don't interact, they don't move
storages. And I built like a, what is
it, like a leather worker, that's part
of on-ramping, part of the early
tutorial, and he just sits in the
building. He doesn't do anything, he
doesn't hunt or anything. You have to
bring the resources to him. He doesn't
build anything. You bring the resources,
you queue it up, and then he takes for
ages. So, essentially, it's a workbench
that you queue stuff and walk away from.
And yet, it has to have its own house,
it has to be built with resources and
manned by a dude that you have to feed,
as well. Now, right at the end of my
time with this, I unlocked some sort of
farmstead, which, it would seem, it does
what the lumberjack does. It will
harvest fields in surrounding. But that
took hours to get to. So, yeah, maybe
the solutions are there, but the pacing
is absolutely bloated as anything from
the beginning out. And then this circles
me back to the UX complaint. The way
that the game laid itself out belies, to
me, something that you see often with
devs, indie devs, is they spend 5 years,
every day, hours and hours every day
with the same build. And they forget.
Every hour that you invest in building
up your end game or whatever, you know,
is another step further away from the
initial player experience, which is the
most important part. The problems you
should have with your game is, "Hey, the
intro was excellent and fantastic, and I
loved it, and then maybe it gets weak at
the end." But that's not how it works.
It's back to front. They become
over-familiar with their build, and they
forget what it is to be a new player,
fresh face going into it. So much so,
the way that the game telegraphed was
there's a big bird boss in the region.
You're going to have to fight it. You're
going to have to gear up towards
fighting it, etc. Right? Okay, cool.
First thing I do is build every single
building possible because that's what
you do in these kind of games. And that
bloody takes forever cuz you're grinding
and getting resources and all and that's
fine. It's still novel, whatever. But
then you hit a ceiling pretty quick and
the only buildings that you do have, you
know, I've got houses full of unemployed
people that I have to feed that do
nothing. Like not like you kind of
assume that they're going to gather
resources on their own or do something.
They don't even cook. So if you put food
in the food storage, you can put raw
food in that in there, but they won't
cook it. And all you really have is like
a lumberjack generating logs, which is
one half of the equation. You often need
stones and the quarry isn't unlocked at
this point. Do you sort of see what I
mean? It's this flimsy halfway there.
And then, you know, you got your bloody
leather worker that does nothing other
than gives you of resource recipes like,
you know, hat, chest, legs, that sort of
thing and they all require pelts. Sure,
whatever. You have to grind unironically
bloody 20 bear pelts for the first
opening hours. That is going to be a
no-go for most people. I use that as a
low-hanging joke for World of Warcraft.
But no, that's the actual gameplay core
here. Anyway, you can build an altar and
you've got a god kind of helping guide
you along. You can put stuff on the
altar and, you know, sacrifice it up as
an offering. And a lot of them are
undiscovered.
So all of a sudden all these resources
I'm going out, I'm just jamming into the
altar to figure out what is offerable.
Now it would seem, don't do that. If
you're listening, don't do that. I know
you want to. I know you probably already
did if you're coming here afterwards.
That's what I did. That's what everyone
would do. That's not what you're
supposed to do. Even though the game is
clearly telegraphing the intrigue
component into it. What you're supposed
to do is fight the boss, which I went
and poked a little bit and I got
absolutely fucking stomped by, but
you're supposed to grind up every piece
of equipment that you can possibly do.
Legs, arms, chest, spi- spears, pile
them, crossbows. You have to build all
of this basic crap on your own back
without really any help from your
villagers. And then you got to go fight
the boss, which can be best described as
a weaker attempt to Dark Souls-ify the
combat, right? It's a boss fight that
often has you stagger into zombies or
boars or wild animals who will third
party and really mess you up because
even if you have half the leather gear
that you're supposed to have, they're
going to three-tap you. And the the
telegraphs are inconsistent and uh it's
just a miserable boss fight, if we're
being honest. The way I beat it in the
end was cheese it by building 300 arrows
for my bow and arrow. And I don't even
necessarily want to get down into it,
but you know, examples are you he has
like a mid-fight change of move set,
introduces electricity that doesn't
telegraph, there's no marker on the
health bar. And then it's a really big,
wide effect that just explodes. It's not
like he winds up or anything like that.
So, the first time you discover it is
because it's going to beat you because
you actually made progress on the boss
fight. And that's not a really good way
to look after your players' interests.
But then you consider if you put a
shield on, you can just block one of his
moves, this sort of dive as a bird. In
fact, you can counter timer it and get
in a boost to melee damage. But his main
sort of attack where he attacks the
ground, you cannot block at all. Like it
just goes through your shield and
damages like half your health. And the
rolling around dodging is so
inconsistent. Like this game is trying
to be a high-fidelity boss fight action
combat game, but it doesn't have the
chops to hang. And so I'd be curious how
many people go the cheese route that I
did, right? I figured out that you can
charge the bow and arrow a little bit to
get a bit more damage. And yeah, I
killed the boss by shooting him with
bloody 150 arrows. Not exactly how they
intended it, I'm sure, and I bet you
it's how most people play it. And as you
can imagine, to come back and hopefully
finish up on my UX point, cuz I don't
want to talk about this bloody game
anymore. When I first played the boss, I
gave it a couple of goes, and you know,
it's like dipping your toes in the
water. You're a gamer, you know what's
going on, and you figure out pretty
quickly that this dude is a fucking
bullet sponge with kind of unpleasant
timers. The chances are you're going to
do the same internal decision as I am,
which is this probably isn't where I'm
supposed to be at right now. I mean, it
is, but you, with your gamer intuition,
are probably going to go and explore the
rest of the map, and that's what I did.
I just started exploring other biomes. I
found like a weird dungeon that would
lock you in, and it was way too high
level, but you couldn't get out of it.
But then all of a sudden, for some
reason, I could get out of it when I
grind against it, but then my dude would
glitch through a wall and die
consistently trying to get my loot out
of the dungeon.
So yeah, if you followed the obscured,
obfuscated critical path that the devs
have in their mind that they have done
everything to not intuit to the player,
then maybe you would be quicker to beat
that first boss, and then in turn unlock
more upgrades, cuz me beating that boss
then tripped more blueprints, more
buildings that I can unlock, right? And
then the game's opening up, go help
other gods or whatever. Presumably it's
a little bit Shadow of the Colossus, go
to the corners of the globe and beat
these bosses, right? And now I've got
some more buildings available, but by
the time I got to that point, I'm
exhausted. I'm hours in, I'm kind of
miserable, and I don't want to play the
game, regardless of whether it's a genre
for me. So Remnants did, it's got
problems, and it's got the sort of
problems, i.e. the disconnect of the
developer telegraphing their game to a
player who is trying their best to
intuit on like good faith what they are
supposed to do, and because of that
disconnect, I can only imagine the next
half a dozen to dozen hours are they're
to be equally difficult and teeth
pulling of an exercise. So, my advice,
make sure you're really into this genre,
right? You've played 10 billion hours of
Necesse or Terraria or whatever. You
probably got a group of mates that you
play with. And even then, maybe get this
on sale. Make sure you really know what
you're getting into before you pull the
trigger. Anyway, I think I've said my
piece. What an exercise in frustration.
At your own risk, team. Much as I leave
it there for the time being and I'll
catch you guys on the next one.