...
Guys, that developers here have been
kind enough to send me a full review key
of the game well in advance. So, I've
had plenty of time to get to know its
quirks and features. This video is
intended so you as a buyer know
everything you need to know. What works,
what doesn't, and who this game is for.
Let me tell you up front that I
absolutely loved the majority of what
this game does. It is very enjoyable,
and there is a ton of content to be
found here even in early access. The map
is honestly humongous, as you can see
right here for example. Let's start with
the basics. Realm Stedt is a top-down
survival and town builder game set in a
Roman world where everything has gone
wrong. Rome essentially burned down. The
gods went quiet, and now the dead and
all kinds of weird creatures walk around
at night. Your job is to find survivors,
build a massive settlement from nothing,
and slowly piece the civilization back
together. The premise sounds
straightforward, but the game manages to
make [music] almost every part of it
feel like it has some thought behind it.
It really did quite a few times
positively remind me of Valheim. So, the
first thing that genuinely surprised me
is how physical the resource system is.
Most games like this just dump wood and
stone into your inventory. In this game,
logs [music] and rocks and many other
resources, like clay for example, are
actual objects sitting on the ground.
So, you have to walk up to that log,
hoist it onto your shoulder, and carry
it back. It is also interactive. For
example, you can throw rocks at enemies
if something is closing in on you. You
can throw flint on a rock to get flint
shards. You can build wooden carts and
load them up to haul bigger amounts back
from further out. There is something
weirdly satisfying about physically
lugging a massive log back to a
settlement and dropping it at a
construction site. It simply makes the
work feel more real. The building here
works like a lot of other survival games
at the surface level. You place the
blueprint and bring materials to it, but
the towns that can grow out of that
process are genuinely impressive. You
start with basically nothing, just a
campfire and a workbench, and slowly you
end up with stuff like a bakery, a
sawmill, a dedicated farming area, a
perimeter wall, various NPC citizens
doing jobs on their own because yes,
most of the crafting is not done by you.
It is done by your people. Finding
survivors out in the world and bringing
them back is one of my favorite parts.
You give someone a house and assign them
a job and they get on with it. The only
thing I would have loved here is if they
gave the NPCs a bit more personality.
Maybe they can expand on this over the
early access phase. The NPCs do have a
progression system. The longer they
work, the better they get. More about
the open world. The map, like I
mentioned, is pretty damn huge. But
beyond that, what makes it worth
exploring is how much it changes the
further you go out. The game [music] has
tons of different biomes with different
enemies, different resources, a
different atmosphere. You go from these
open plains near your starting area to
forests, various caves, darker and more
dangerous regions the further you push.
Each biome has its own crafting tier,
meaning you need to actually get out
there and explore to keep progressing.
Their god system is honestly one of the
most interesting things in here. Their
progression doesn't only come from
finding better recipes and simply
crafting better gear. You also unlock
new technologies, buffs, and buildings
by making offerings and sacrifices at an
altar to different Roman gods.
Oftentimes, this is tied to a specific
boss. So, it turns the altar into this
ongoing side project. Something that
made me appreciate the world more than I
expected is the way enemies behave on
their own. The different factions and
creatures genuinely fight each other if
they cross paths. For example, I watched
a skeleton absolutely demolish a group
of orcs and this wasn't a scripted
encounter. I've also seen this massive
grizzly bear absolutely annihilate a
horde of undead. Also a cool detail I
like, the blood from those fights sticks
around on the ground for a long time.
After a big battle, you can see exactly
where everything went down. Now, the
game also has farming. This works like
in most other games. You plant seeds,
water your crops,
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; harvest them, and process the results.
Wheat becomes flour. Flour can become
bread and bread becomes a decent
offering to the gods or food for your
citizens. It's not very complex, but it
slots into everything else really
naturally. It also gives you something
calm to do between the more stressful
parts of the game, and it also directly
feeds into the god system. Of course,
with the game being early access and
all,
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; there are some things that are less fun.
For example, if you play solo, because
yes, you can play this game co-op, then
being out at night in the open world
gets exhausting pretty fast. Something
attacks you basically every few seconds,
and the game seems to have spots where
enemies simply respawn endlessly. You're
trying to find a survivor camp or gather
resources, and you just keep getting
interrupted over and over. Getting your
walls up early helps a lot, because at
least then your base stays safe. But out
in the wild, it can get genuinely
relentless. I don't think this is
unsolvable. Better gear and higher
combat skills make a big difference, but
especially early on, it can feel like
the game is just constantly pestering
you. Boars in particular are really
nasty early on. One literally attacked
me during the tutorial, and almost
killed me. The dungeons and traps in
particular can also feel unfair in a way
that goes beyond just being hard. There
are traps in there with bad design.
There's no visual indicator, no sound,
nothing that indicates that stepping on
them is instant death. You can retrieve
your stuff at the place of death, but
sometimes this is a massive march. The
combat itself is pretty nice, actually.
You have the regular attacks, a dodge, a
heavy attack if you hold the button
down, and you can also use scrolls and
stuff. You pick a profession at the
start that shapes your opening gear and
gives you a slight direction to build
toward. Most fights in the open world
are manageable, but the dungeon fights
are a different story. The bosses can
also feel like massive damage sponges.
I'm not quite sure if the game scales
the HP based on how many players are
playing. If that isn't the case, then
they should absolutely implement this.
The full game is still in early access,
with the developers estimating around 1
or 2 years in early access, they will
add more biomes, more bosses, and of
course more general content are planned.
What is already here feels like a real
game though. It's not a skeleton. And of
course, like I mentioned, there are ways
to improve, but the systems already
nicely connect to each other. The world
has personality and it feels
atmospheric. And the progression
definitely gives you enough to chase
that you don't run out of things to do
quickly. Personally, I'm definitely
planning to add another 30 to 40 hours
of play time here. Even with the
frustrating bits, I found myself
genuinely not wanting to stop playing.
And currently this doesn't happen too
often. This already says more than
anything else I could say here. And this
sentence concludes today's video. If
your time was respected, a like or
comment is very much appreciated.