...
What's up guys and gals? Welcome back to
the Nerd Castle. Today in the world of
indie games, we're going to be checking
in on a title called Romestead. We had
an opportunity to take a look at a
limited demo of this game oh 3 or 4
months ago. Well, the early access
version is now out and so it's time for
us to do an appraisal to decide whether
or not it deserves your buckage. So,
that's exactly what we're going to do.
If you've never seen Romestead before,
let me get you up to speed here.
Romestead is a game where the Roman
Empire has fallen to a zombie
apocalypse. All of their pantheon, their
gods have been scattered to the wind and
lost their memories. And you are an
openw world survival RPG guy that's
starting up a township that's trying to
reawaken the memory of the old gods by
donating all kinds of stuff to them,
doing their quests, helping them find
their relics, all those sorts of things
so that they can bring back the glory of
the empire. So far, I've been playing
the game for about 2, three hours. I
think that's about enough for first
impressions. And truth be told, they're
positive. I actually think this is one
of the better survival games that we've
gotten in a bit of time. It's been a
good year for survival games. We've
gotten a whole bunch of them that are
pretty solid, and Romestead is no
different. Uh, if after watching this
you wanted to check the game out for
yourself, it's reasonably cheap. It's
now being sold as part of a package, I
think, for $11, which is actually a
pretty banger deal for the amount of
artistic fidelity and whatnot you're
getting out of this title. And then you
can also find a bunch of other Nerd
Castle links down there, just in case
you wanted to give them the old saucy
click. But without further ado, let's
dive on into it. I will introduce you to
my Roman city, and hopefully we'll have
a good time here today as I show off
some of the things that make this game
fun and special. So, here we are inside
of Bootius Maximus. That's the village
that I've created for myself. It's the
village that It's the village that I
always wanted to create. I feel like I
would be an exceptionally awesome
magistrate. So, inside Bootius Maximus,
you're going to be doing all the things
that you do in other games like Rim
World. Uh there are supply chains, there
are different buildings that produce
different things, there are stoages,
there are wood cutters, there are
stonemasons, all that kind of stuff. And
all of it is done to a very high level
of detail. To give you an example of
that, if you want to, let me throw some
wheat inside of here. If you want to
mill wheat, you've actually got to push
the millstone around. You put wheat
inside of there and then you hang out
and you push this thing until you get
your 75 flour or whatever else it is.
You can also put olives inside of there.
I haven't experimented with it too much
to see what I can put inside of it, but
it seems like there are a number of
things that I can put inside the
millstone. This over here is the altar
and also the rallying flag. These are
going to be the central positions of
your entire society. The first is going
to allow you to donate to the gods. So
the way that the RPG works in this game
is that you get experience with the
different gods by donating them items
that they respect. So in the case of
Vulcan, if you give him crafted items,
he is very happy about that. In the case
of Venus, if you give her gems or you
give her amulets or tokens of love, she
will like that. In the case of who is
this right here? In the case of Mercury,
he's the god of trade. So, anything you
put inside of there, like money or gold
bars or anything else will make him
happy. He will level up. Each of these
gods has a talent tree. As you go
through, it will unlock new buildings
that you can build inside of your
society and also give your citizens
things like damage resistance. It will
allow them to fight a little bit harder
because over time, I haven't seen this
mechanic yet in the first two or three
hours. This game starts out pretty
lacadasically and allows the player to
sort of get their footing and do
whatever the hell they want, which I
appreciate. I I haven't been attacked by
zombies or anything yet, but that
doesn't mean it won't happen in the
future. I think I'm only on like the
third or fourth storyline main quest
right now. I've actually been making
sure that I always have enough armor. I
always have enough weapons. I always
have the things that I need in order to
explore the next area before I move
through with the storyline quests. In
return, when they hit certain threshold
levels or your main storyline quest gets
to certain levels, they will give you
personal quests. These personal quests
will unlock more buildings. Uh, they
will unlock legendary gear that you can
craft. This game is absolutely filled to
the brim with random magical items. They
drop off of enemies. They drop inside of
dungeons. They drop from quests. Uh,
there are loads and loads of things in
this game that you can get all of
something like Terraria that are not
craftable. So, the craftable gear is
good, don't get me wrong, but the stuff
that you get from the gods, the stuff
you get from dungeons, it tends to be a
little bit better or it tends to be a
version of like the crafting gear that
doesn't have the downsides of the
crafting gear. An example being if
you're wearing heavy armor, yeah, you're
really protected from melee attacks, but
you're probably going to be slow, you're
going to have bad stamina, and you're
going to be weak to magic. uh godly
items and things you get out of dungeons
tend to be the best of both worlds where
they've got like really good defense
with no discernable downsides. The thing
is though, you got to go do those
dungeons and they can be definitely a
little bit intense. You will run for
your life and so there is a little bit
of challenge to this game as well. For
right now, what I've been working on is
that I've got myself a blacksmith up
here. This is allowing me to do ore
processing. And so I do have a
blacksmith on this side that has a
number of things that he can create for
me to make my life a little bit better.
I did want to make some copper thread. I
felt like that was a really good idea.
The crafters that you assign, you find
people that have been scattered to the
winds all throughout the map. If you
have a building available that they can
live inside of, you can bring them back
over here and they will work inside
here. They level up at that job. You
will see with some of these blueprints
over here, they need to be a certain
level of crafting before they're going
to be able to make this stuff for you.
But for now, there's a couple of
upgrades that I've been working on. So,
I did want to upgrade all my crafting
tools. I did conceivably want to upgrade
some of my weapons, too. I may have
enough copper on hand to actually get
that done. It's very difficult to say,
but let's go grab a little bit of extra
copper first, just to be sure of it.
Then, I'll introduce you to a few more
buildings. I don't know where a copper
mine's going to be out here, but I got
to go find a copper node. The game does
have vehicles, so you can get carts and
stuff that allow you to carry more items
with you when you're transporting
things. things are distributed into two
different groups. There's stuff that can
fit in your backpack and in your
pockets, and then there's stuff that
cannot. You have to hold it up above
your head, Legend of Zelda style. The
card is for those items so that you can
carry more than one of them at a time
while you're out on a farming run. Now,
because it's daytime right now, there's
not going to be there will be threats
out here that we may run into, but Oh,
is there a guy over here? Hold on.
There's a guy over here. I didn't know
there I need some sticks, too. Let me
break some trees and some bushes real
quick to get some sticks so that I can
make my crafting gear so that I can
craft a little faster. Uh the game is
completely and totally filled with
secrets. I'm pretty sure almost
everything in this game you can possibly
break open has a chance to be a chest.
And so I'll get this right now. The game
does have Terraria style relics that you
can attach to your character that give
you different bonuses. Be it for defense
or they might make you move a little bit
faster or they might make your arrows
travel faster or something else like
that. I just fell into oi. Yo, we just
got Grand Theft Cardo, dude. Nah, man.
You better stop that right this second.
Uh, these guys right here will walk off
with just about anything you lay around.
One time I saw one walk up, pick up a
squirrel, and put it on his head, and
then just like leave with a squirrel on
his head. When I say there is nothing
they won't steal, I'm being 100% serious
with you. Let me mark this guy. The game
does give you a pretty solid dollop of
mapping tools so that you can mark
things that you find on the map uh when
you find them. I've got two people
waiting in the wings right now to be
recruited, but I don't have workspaces
for any of them yet. So, I've just been
kind of passively marking them as I
cruise around the territory. Let me go
down here and see if I can find myself a
copper mine real fast. No copper, but I
did find coal, which is actually pretty
good. Your character does have Skyrim
style attributes that level up as you
play through the game as well. What the
benefits are of those are not
immediately apparent a lot of the time.
So like right now I'm level 15 or I'm
like level 16 at mining. My mining
damage has not gone up at all. But I
don't know if that's due to the fact
that I'm still using rusty tools that
I've had since the beginning of the
game, which coincidentally is why I'm
trying to update my tools right now is
so I can test a theory. I'm guessing it
adds an amount of damage that is
percentile related, but my percentile is
so small right now that it doesn't
really matter in the greater scheme of
things. Yeah, there's one of them right
there stealing a rat. He's got a rat on
his head. I told you those little guys
are hilarious if you watch them for a
little while. But if you don't watch
them, they will walk off with your
stuff. There's a copper node. It's not
going to be much of a copper node. I was
hoping we would get more than one, but
you know, for whatever reason, this game
does like using uh just random digits.
So, when you're attacking anything in
this game, I got to get my thoughts
straight here for how I want to word
this. You'll have like a little text
right there, 35 out of 35, that tells
you how much HP the thing has that
you're attacking. I would recommend that
they move it on over to just a health
bar for everything inside of the game.
It's not that bad for when you're
harvesting out in the field. Oh, Jesus.
Okay, let's run away. Uh, I am being
attacked by a boar storm right now.
Luckily, my armor should make boar
damage. Oh well, maybe I was wrong.
Never mind. Boore damage appears to be
relevant. Okay, well, now that I'm
getting my ass whooped by pigs out in
the middle of nowhere, kill you off,
too. The good news here is I need that
meat for feeding my people. We've got to
put meat into a like a meat chest. We've
got a large chest of meat inside the
center of our city and our people eat
out of it and they get a debuff if they
haven't eaten in a while. Is that a
dungeon right there? Maybe I should go
down and check on it. It looks like a
dungeon. And dungeons too have they do
have pretty rad treasure. The Caster's
Tomb. Is that how you pronounce that
word? I don't know how. Ow. Okay. Yeah,
death laser. Sure. Absolutely. Uh don't
want to be anywhere near the death
laser. Looks like she's also got a
tracking magic. Oh, it's a it's a ray of
frost. It slows you down. Okay, so I
need you to go away. And as you can see,
the entire game is magnificently well
animated. The megas Manurva scroll. I
have never seen that item before. I got
to break this thing real fast.
Otherwise, going to keep spawning zedi
boys on top of me. So, it looks like
some kind of dark ritual was happening
down here. The good news is zombies
aren't really a threat to me anymore.
What does this do? It gives me bolt.
Hell yeah, dude. That's way better than
what I've got. Okay, so it looks like it
does two things. It looks like it sucks
stuff towards me. I think it's just an
environmental effect. All of Dragon Ball
Z, you know, like when they're charging
up like a
and they're like charging up and the
stones start levitating and sort of
gravitating towards them. I think that's
what they were going for right there. It
doesn't appear to have any other
gameplay benefit. Either way though, I
got myself a new magic spell, which is
great. I haven't decided if I'm going to
be like a melee character or like a
spellb blade yet. I'm sort of on the
fence of it. Can this be broken? There's
going to be a chest inside of here. Huh?
I want the goodies. Give me the goodies.
Uh, there was indeed a chest inside of
there. It's a lower tier chest, though,
so it's not going to be that exciting.
The good news is we got an offering to
the gods, and it looks like we've got
lucky dice, which give us higher crit
chance, which I think is pretty awesome
in all fairness. Like having a little
bit more crit would be a good idea. Does
it mark this thing as completed when I
knock it out? Yeah, cleared. All right,
that's exactly the type of quality of
life that I love to see. Let's continue
carting this back home. And when we get
there, oop, don't want to do that. And
when we get there, we'll start smelting
off some copper. We'll getting some arts
and crafts done and hopefully land
oursel in a world of upgrades. That's my
farm right there. I've got a farm worker
that just plants stuff. That's pretty
much it. You put seeds inside the chest
inside of there and she goes out and
just plants everything where it needs to
be planted. I don't know if she
harvests. I don't know if I've seen her
harvesting just yet, but I would figure
she does. It would be odd if she didn't.
Let's go ahead and smelt the ore. We can
do that by just chucking it into the
furnace real quick. There we go. Now we
got them sparks flying. And once we got
ourselves a few more copper bars, I'll
be able to make myself a new suit of
armor, a new set of crafting tools, and
things should go faster. and Swifter
from there. All nice and done. So, we
will throw those inside his supply chest
so that he has them available. I'll
throw the sticks in there, too. And I
definitely wanted a copper pickaxe. I
wanted a copper axe. And then I think
I'll probably just take the copper
gladius because right now mine does six
to seven damage, but it's got minus 50%
attack speed or something like that,
which then makes it difficult to
utilize. I can also make a copper chest
plate. I don't have a good chest piece
right now. I'll have him make that, too,
while we're just in the neighborhood.
And that's a pretty solid chunk of
crafting right there. I'm curious to see
how much XP he gets from doing like a
bigger craft like this. Uh, the answer
is not that much. It was like a little
tiny sliver. So, I get the vibe that I'm
probably just going to have him uh sit
on doing just like tiny jobs. So, I've
got 11 of those left. I don't know how
much he gets. Actually, I may not need
the chest piece because you've no doubt
noticed my super kawaii hat that I'm
wearing right here. Thank you. I
appreciate you calling it maximum
kawaii. Uh, I looted I killed a giant
bird that was flying through the sky.
You saw him when we covered the demo. I
murdered him. And this is the hat I got
for murdering him. And it's like far and
away better than every other hat that I
have. I did. I made a chest piece over
here. And it matches our other set item.
So, we might as well put that on real
quick. That's good because my leather
armor unfortunately didn't really have a
lot going for it. Sometimes you get mods
on this stuff when you're doing crafted
gear Diablo style. So like this is the
Bullwarks leather armor. Uh it's got
knockback resistance on it. So that does
add a little bit of flavor and like a
reason to recraft the same item over and
over and over again. But for right now,
I'm going to stick with the items that I
carved away from a giant bird monster
hunter style that the gods have rewarded
me with. I've also got Rudy boots over
here. Dude, Rudy boots are pretty sick.
I got these out of a dungeon. And
honestly, they've been better than every
other boot that I've had so far. Let me
handle some of the cooking and cleaning
and other stuff that Oh, it's foggy out
here. Does that mean I'm about to get
attacked? I bet it does. Okay. Well, I'm
going to craft up some bread so that we
can feed it to the people. Bread and
circuses, you know what I mean? The main
attribute of the Roman Empire.
And then I'm going to put it inside the
food crate real fast. Everything can be
transferred rapidly just by
right-clicking on it. That is something
that I appreciate tremendously. A lot of
games are lacking that very, very simple
quality of life. A lot of games lack
that quality of life. And I appreciate
that they put it in here. Like I play a
lot of survival games where logistical
considerations and just menu
interactions and whatnot have not been
thought about very well all the way
through. And as a result, you find
yourself fiddling with menus more than
playing the game. I like playing the
game, don't get me wrong. I'll fiddle
with a menu every now and again, but uh
I'd like to play the game, too. Let's do
our donations real fast. We'll see if we
get any god points out of any of this
stuff. Yeah, I'll throw that all in
there. Uh the meter's moved a little
bit, but nobody leveled up. We do have a
quest right now where they want me to
donate some pine nuts, some cabbage,
some mint, and some bay leaf, and
that'll unlock the bakery, I think. Oh,
a well. That would be useful. Where's
the moonring at? Is that off to the
east? It's in the decayed grotto down
there. I strongly suggest we go get that
because having a well will mean that my
farmer can actually water her crops and
in so watering they will grow a lot
faster. Uh some quality of life is
lacking a little bit in this game. Does
she actually harvest this stuff or does
it kind of just leave it up to me to
harvest it? Because I'm worried I'm
going to murder the rest of my plants
while harvesting over here. Does it? Oh,
if they're not fully grown, they don't
get muck ducked. Well, that's good.
Okay. Well, I'll just go through and do
the harvest every now and again if I
have to. But right now though, I
strongly feel like we should go get the
moonring because that'll punch up our
farming to the next level. I've got
enough food to where I feel safe doing
this. My armor levels are decently high,
so I'm just going to head down that way.
We'll do ourselves a dungeon. Uh, we'll
get the well unlocked. And then we'll
figure out kind of reappraise and figure
out what we want to do next after I
finish that off. Yo, this magic spell is
the Hell yeah, dude. It's
one-shotting zombies. We got another
bird over here. Should I fight the bird
again while it's respawned?
I think I probably should just to get
materials off of it. It also drops
treasure. Like, it drops a big ass
chest. Oh god, I've been crushed and
I've been crushinated. Okay. Uh, dash
away from that thing for right now.
I was not expecting to have to deal with
this many zombies while I was out in the
field, but let's give it a little bit of
room.
And if I can just put a little bit of
heat on this board, I think we'll be out
of here shortly. Luckily, the guardian
of Manurva is super easy to kite out.
Uh, just don't get hit is my advice. If
you get hit, there's not a lot of
windows in this fight uh to get your HP
back by eating because eating in this
game, like an Estus Flask, sort of locks
you in one space for a little bit. Okay,
lightning storm. Don't like that. Dash
over that way cuz I don't know how big
the AoE is going to be when the bird
comes down. But this game is capable of
actually having much larger boss fights
as well because it takes place in a
realm of mythology. I like that very
much. I think that's cool. I like the
big monsters that take up a fatty chunk
of the screen. Let's finish this thing
off real quick.
There we go. 17 damage wasn't ideal, but
I'll take it. I've already killed that
boss, so she wasn't going to be
particularly difficult for me because
I'm a next tier up. Oh, she dropped the
chest piece. Okay. Uh, when consumed, a
pretty flower. When consumed by a
citizen, it gives them happiness. We got
some free copper and we got a donated
eye that we can give to the gods. I
don't know if that can be used for
crafting anything. I haven't seen
anything that crafts with it so far, but
it is a legendary item. And so I'm sort
of thinking it might be useful to have a
You stop that right now. I'm sort of
thinking it might be useful to have
around. Now, as we get out here into the
woods, we may have some antagonists that
want to take us down. If it's just pigs,
frankly, that would be optimal in this
given situation. He fell into the water.
Everything in this game drowns when it
falls into water. So, if you get
yourself a pretty awesome knockback
spell, water can be very helpful for
getting a lot of enemies off of you.
Kill him off. Is this the place that I'm
trying to be right now? I think it is.
We also have another villager over here.
So, I'll mark that very rapidly so that
we know where he's at. I was wondering
why. So, in this game, decorative items,
you unlock them by destroying them out
inside the game world. I was wondering
why when I destroyed a well, I didn't
get access to build a well. That's
because it's quest locked. Gotcha. Break
the door open and then down into the
decayed grotto we go. I do like enemy
volume in this game as well. Like I've
talked about this in the past, but I'm a
big fan of stuff like Path of Exile
where the entire screen is full of stuff
that's trying to kill you. Is there any
way to get over to that spawner? I bet
that's going to open up. Oh, that spawns
things, too. All right. Well, let's take
him down. I have found that the game is
really well balanced for solo, by the
way, which makes me pretty happy. Uh, I
don't know how I'm going to do that. H
I think I got to sit something. Oh,
there's a rock. There we go. I'll put
the rock on top of it. Perfect. Did it
open the one over there? It did not.
Okay, that's fine. Let's deal with all
these guys real quick first. Just
beautiful animation inside of this game.
You can tell that whoever dedicated
themselves to doing the art for this
title applied themselves and was both
passionate and in love with the subject
matter because there's so many little
details while you're going through the
game and the way that just random
enemies interact with the world with the
way that you interact with the world
with the momentum of the characters
stuff like that. Who's this guy right
here? Let me break him out of jail real
quick.
Okay, you've been broke it out of jail.
Roma's in ruins and I lost my farm. Do
you have a place to stay? I don't
unfortunately. So, I'm going to have to
come back for you. For whatever reason
in this game, building houses does not
give you more popc
...
uh what ends up happening is you can
only build like a personal house for
yourself and the people actually live
inside the workshops. Let me break this
thing down real Oh, I can open it. Oh,
okay. Well, that works for me. We got
the moonring. I think it was letting me
loot a chest that was actually inside of
it. So, that might have been a bug right
there, but not that big of a deal. I got
my looties. And so, now we can scoot on
out of here, head back to town, donate
that moon string to the gods, and get
ourselves a little bit of favor. Some of
this stuff is watered over here. I don't
know if she watered it or if the rain
watered it. This guy has a quest. You
lost your wine, and I'd really like to
have it back. Yeah, I did the same thing
with my tequila. I totally lost it. I
would like another one for free. Uh,
let's donate the moonring over here. You
honor the way of the hunt. Good. And so
now we can build the well. I'll probably
actually try to get most of this stuff
done here today. I need crystallized
blood in order to unlock technology for
pottery, a beer dolium, or we can get a
quarry down there. I think the quarry is
probably the most useful thing. I need
to donate six copper bars to Vulcan for
him to favor me. So, we'll go do that
real fast. But that does mean that I'm
going to have to go out and farm a lot
of stuff to make this all work. I'm
going to donate that. I'm going to
donate that because I don't need the
gear. A torn pelt. That probably goes to
the gods. I'll donate that, too. Let's
just donate everything, man. Give it all
up to the gods.
That did give me a skill point that I
can play around with. So, like I don't
know who I want to level up right now.
We can get more baker experience gain.
We can get more seeds from wild crops.
That actually sounds kind of helpful. I
might throw that together. That feels
like a thing that might assist. What do
you have? I lost my wine. You lost wine,
too. Everybody's losing wine around
here. I think you guys are just
alcoholics if I'm being honest with you.
I will finish off that quest right there
for the quarry. And let's see where we
can actually put a quarry down because
Oh, I've got a market, too. Yeah, the
market sounds actually pretty stellar.
I'm running out of places to put things,
but I will put the market right there
because I have all this money and I
haven't been able to spend it as of yet.
And then we have a quarry over here.
Does it need to have stones inside of
its radius? Don't think it does. So,
I'll just plop it down right there. And
then we'll use the materials in order to
get it done. But I am going to have to
do a significant amount of clay
harvesting to build up all this stuff.
Oh, there is a new house over here that
allows me to store up citizens.
I'm just bad at the game. Okay. All
right. I'm fine with that. I'll take it
on the chin for the greater for the
greater good here. Uh let's put in a
house right there. And we'll leave rude
for a road right there because I was
going to get rid of these fields over
here. Anyways, I would like to get rid
of this crop field right here, but
they're not making it easy. Well, it
doesn't count as any of the types of
demolition that I'm trying to do right
now. So, maybe it'll just despawn on its
own. I'm not really too sure. But first
things first, this needs another stone.
So, we'll throw that on in there. You do
have to build all or bring all the
building materials to the building that
you're trying to construct. I have
noticed that with the construction
skill, uh, it actually changes the
amount of meter you get when you play
the miniame. So, these guys want rocks,
they want wood, they want a whole bunch
of stuff. All right. Well, let's just
bust this open real quick and I'll start
gathering up some of the thingies that I
need in order to make this all function.
Although, I think I may have to go fetch
a cart in order to make this go a little
bit more rapido. Uh, so I need eight
logs. All right, let me go find the cart
and I'll bring that over. Cart's right
here. So, I'll hook that up. We'll grab
that right there. Throw two logs in
there. Then, we'll go back this way.
I've got a bunch of logs in storage
right now, so it shouldn't be that bad
to fill up on, you know,
things that are big and round and wood.
We'll grab you. There we go. I don't
think this holds five. I think it holds
four. Yeah, it holds four. All right, so
it's going to be like a multi-rip type
deal. Wood has been deposited. So, now
it's time for the more complex part. I
need to get clay. I'm going to show you
how to do this because a bunch of people
on the forums have been like, "I can't
find clay anywhere. How the hell do I do
clay?" Clay's actually really easy. You
just got to have a bucket and then you
need to go to a place where there's
water. Any lake will usually do it, like
a lake or a pond. There will almost
always be at least one tile of clay over
there. Mine is down here, so it's
actually not that far of a run. And then
you just fill it up right there. You
throw it back in the cart. I have had
trouble with selectivity of getting the
thing out of the cart that I actually
want to take out of the cart, but you
know, that's life. Everything doesn't
work perfectly. Like I said, there's
still some missing quality of life in
this game that would definitely spruce
it up a little bit. Throw those in
there. And don't worry, we do get the
buckets back after we build this thing,
so you're not caught in like a
never-ending cycle of bucket crafting. I
don't think anybody plays a game like
this to craft buckets, but you know, uh,
no citizen assigned. Assign a citizen to
this building at the town core. Okay, so
we're going to get ourselves a vendor
over here. I'm curious to see what's
actually going to be on Oh, they're all
going to the market to check it out.
Nice. Okay, well, I need to go pick up
those citizens then from down south. So,
I think I'll probably go get them. I
need to get my olive oil done as well.
So, maybe I'll bang that out, too. I'm
not really too sure. Actually, screw
that. We should just go on jolly
adventures, dude. That's what I'm
feeling right now. I'm feeling like
jolly good adventures are the thing that
I would wish to have were I an
adventurer. So maybe we'll go do some
jolly good adventuring. I got to hit
another dungeon anyways. Uh just for the
gods. So like I'm gonna go do that. I
don't know if this is our place, but
it's kind of looking like our place.
There's a lot of zombies over here. So
like we got a big one, too. Let's knock
him out real quick. Occasionally the
zombies drop relics or gear, but not
very often. Like, it's not one of those
things you're going to be able to rely
on at all. Keep wiping guys out. We're
going to have a lot more zombie
problems, too, because in my infinite
wisdom, I decided to do this at night.
This has got to be the place. This place
is huge, and it is ornate. I'm going to
break all the crates, though, because I
would love to have a few more uh wooden
planks. Hey, bay leaves. Nice, dude. I
think I need those for a quest. Hell
yeah. Down into the dungeon. The buried
fort.
What you guys got to show me over here?
Anything interesting? Is that a spawner?
That's not a spawner. Okay, give me
these wooden planks over here.
Ow.
I have found range to be a lot safer in
this game than other play styles. But
then again, I haven't really fooled
around with like getting shields or
anything either that might block an
attack or allow me to mitigate. We got
golden scales. I think I know of a god
that would probably appreciate that as a
donation. What do we have over Oh,
that's a pit right there. I couldn't
tell that was a pit with the dart going
on. Okay. Well, won't throw myself into
any pits any further. We got arrows down
here. All right. See if I can avoid
getting knocked into any death pits. I
feel like they must be spending a
fortune on ammunition for a booby trap
like this. Although it is kind of weird
that they just come straight out of the
wall. There's no like device or anything
on the wall that makes it happen. Oh,
I've got to like throw something onto
those. Okay, let me see what I can do
here. I don't know how long my throw is.
I mean, I got it. I got it on the first
go. That's not bad. And unless I want to
go through the spike trap again, I've
got to go through the arrow trap while
holding this over my head so that I can
pin the other one down. I see what
they're getting at right now. They were
testing my herculean perception. Was
perception something that Hercules was
known for? I don't know. Either way, we
got this whole thing done. So, I'll just
sit that down right there. Break all
this stuff to get my goodies. All right.
And what's inside the chest? Inside the
chest, we have crystallized blood from a
god. Sanguis Celeste. We got a little
bit more copper, which is great because
I'm sure Oh, we got the basher. It's a
named weapon. All right, we got the
spoils of war. So, the god of war will
probably want that. And then I'm almost
positive the goddess of love is going to
enjoy that. Amethyst, a fish sauce used
in a plethora of dishes to bring out
salty flavor. No, I'm good. Not a big
fish and seafood guy, which is kind of
odd for having grown up near the ocean
my entire life. I have never liked
seafood. Like I do like crustaceians.
Like I enjoy crab or like some scraps or
like some prawns or like some mud bugs.
I like those, but I've never really
enjoyed fish. I don't know. There's
something about the fishy smell and the
fishy flavor that just puts me off my
lunch instantaneously. I'm just like,
nah, I don't like it. It stinks. H.
There is a goddess shrine over here. I
was moving my way. I was trying to give
you guys another dungeon while I was out
in the field, but there is a goddess
shrine over here. If we light a fire in
front of it, uh technically
something should happen, but I don't
know exactly what. I'll plop that down
right there. Uh the divine flame reveals
a location on your map. The champion of
Manurva awaits.
It's probably just taking me back to the
to the bird and so I I think there's
multiple of them on the map just in case
you don't run into the ones that they
give you. All right, dungeon. Are you
going to be like a longer dungeon or
like a shorter dungeon? There are
different sizes of dungeons. I know that
all the dungeons I've gone to have been
tiny thus far and did not have much to
them, but there are larger ones. We just
haven't gotten lucky enough to get
those. I'm going to hit these guys from
right here cuz I'm a cheese ball. Yeah,
there we go. Swords level 16. I think
sometimes when you stat up your skills,
you end up getting favors. Yeah. So,
I've got favors over here, too. We got
another skill tree that we can play
around with. I'll probably make my
pickaxes and my axes stronger. I will
more than likely Let's get more
lighting. I don't really care about
sleep regeneration, but I'll take it.
And then I'll take more melee attack
power. That sounds good. I thought it
was giving me a gift of the gods
whenever I got those level ups. So, I
think that's what it does like as you
get skill points in different skills. It
just gives you general character levels.
And so, the buried fort. Oh, this one's
got the same layout as the last one.
Well, that's not good. That means you
need more variety right there,
developers. That's what that means is
that you don't have enough tile sets in
your early access to keep people
compelled. This is a thing that I
definitely don't like to see. For all
the praise that I have put on this game
the entire time we've been playing it
for how much I like it. Uh, I do not
like that. That sucks. Well, let's see
what's inside of our chest at least.
Maybe we can get some fun loot. Globy.
What is Globy? Dough balls from cheese
and semolina coated in honey. That
sounds that sounds pretty rad. I think I
could probably get down on that. I don't
know. I'm always pretty open-minded, but
I think I commented on that the last
time we played the game where I was
like, "What the hell is semolina?" And
then I looked it up and I think it was
like a special type of dough or flour or
something like that. Ow. Straight to the
face. It's going to be like that. All
right. Well, let's see what's in the
good chest over here. Obviously, our
quest items going to be inside of here.
I do wish I could make my inventory a
little bit bigger. Take everything you
can. We have the scroll of Diana. I can
also get a protective volley. Oh, it's
giving me stone skin when I when I
channel it. Okay, I must have missed
that when I was looking at the
description. I do like the sound of a
volali. And so I'll give that some
thought. Can probably throw out the
wheat seeds just so I can carry this
back and like donate it to a god. There
we go. And so with two of those knocked
out, let's go back to town. And once I
get there, we will talk about my closing
thoughts in this early access for right
now because I think we're about at that
point. Oh, I can do like a little AoE if
I charge it up. In case you're wondering
what that spell does, that might
actually be super good for harvesting if
I can get the cast time down. But, uh,
closing thoughts about Romestead. I
actually think this is in a really good
spot. I'm getting the same vibe from it
that I got when Graveyard Keeper first
came out. It's a game with very high
visual fidelity that it's clear that the
art team that worked on this game really
applied themselves and did a good job.
Likewise for the soundtrack, except for
there's like this buzzing bug in the
background. I swear to God, there's this
everpresent fly when you're in the
planes that does like this buzzing
throat singing summoning the Sarda car
thing. It's been driving me nuts. Please
take that fly out of the audio mixing. I
swear to God, I've been hearing it for 3
hours. But aside from that, everything
on the presentational side of this game
is very well done. In fact, I'd say
exceptionally well done. It's a very
entertaining game just to look at and
watch somebody play. The sense of
exploration is satisfying. There are
secrets and chests and all kinds of
relics and things to stack all over the
place. And given the fact that even if
you get bad loot out of a chest, it
doesn't really matter because they've
designed this sort of circular system
where any bit of surplus that you have,
you can donate it to the gods in order
to level up your god track. That's a
really smart design decision. It's the
same thing as throwing items in the
trash, but instead this game rewards you
for throwing the items in the trash
because just cuz you don't need them
doesn't mean the gods won't take them as
an offering. So, I think that's actually
a pretty clever little side step right
there that avoids the travail of just
throwing away items that happens in a
lot of other survival games where you
get past a certain tier and now
everything of the previous tier all the
way back to the beginning of the game is
completely and totally useless. I like
that. I like that cleverness that's
baked inside of this game. And so from a
front end, I think this game is really
rad. I think it has a very promising
future. There are a few observations
that I have though. Uh, one of them is
that the city building is lacking a lot
of UI and also just quality of life
stuff. Uh, so for example, if you put
down the footprint of a building, you
cannot delete that footprint or use like
a move function to move it around if
you're slightly dissatisfied with its
spacing. You have to like fully build
the building, then you have to destroy
it using the tool. And there's a number
of buildings I've run into that kind of
do this. I don't know if this is a
universal problem, but I would like to
see that fixed. I should be able to
destroy a blueprint the exact same way
that I destroy a fully built building.
On top of that, I would very much like
to see move and edit functions so that I
don't have to tear things down quite as
frequently and I can rearrange my city
to get it aesthetically pleasing. Uh,
that's one of those city building things
that I expect to see there. Aside from
that, I did find that the dungeon
variety is a little bit limited on
continuing to play the game. You will
see kind of the same copy pasta every
now and again in dungeons that needs to
be expanded out or at least made
procedural to the extent that the player
almost never sees it happen, which means
that you've got a fair bit of dungeon
designing in front of you. I also wish
that the dungeons were longer. A lot of
the dungeons, like I'd say 90% of the
dungeons I went into were just one room.
You solve like a little environmental
puzzle, kill a few mobs, and you're
done. I would like to actually see
proper dungeon crawls inside of this
game. Maybe they're later on in the
game, but in the early game, I only saw
one dungeon that had like eight or nine
rooms that I had to go through doing
challenges before I got to the end. I
think they should all be like that. The
relics are good enough that I feel like
you should have to work for them a
little bit harder. The invasion system
is also interesting. So, you declare war
on zombie settlements and then they
invade you. That means that for those of
you that prefer cozy gaming, you don't
really have to worry about your city
being attacked until you initiate that
attack by clicking on the declaration of
war, which I think is a nice thing for
those sorts of people. I think I would
like a game mode though where like every
x amount of days you get attacked
independent of the declarations of war.
And then the declarations could be in
there for you to get extra battles just
in case because I like some antagonism
in my games. I like games that hit me in
the face like Frost Punk style and
really want me to lose and then like
dance on my grave, you know? I prefer
the games that are all about suffering.
Still, I did find that Romestead is a
really good game. I can't speak to the
depth of the content as of right now or
when it runs out inside their early
access. There is a possibility here that
I would investigate for any prospective
v buyer of just like how many hours
worth of gameplay is in here, how many
biomes, so on and so forth. I did dig
around on the forums a little bit, but
couldn't come to a conclusive answer.
So, I would investigate that if you're a
little bit worried about the fact that
the game is sitting on like a seven out
of 10 rating. That's largely due to the
fact that apparently the game doesn't
work very well. I went through the
reviews to figure this out. Apparently,
the game does not work very well with
controllers and it does not work very
well with the Steam Deck. I have neither
of those two things. I was playing
entirely with the mouse and keyboard
where the game works fantastically well
and exactly how you would expect from
this kind of game, but if you're
planning on playing on those platforms,
I would investigate a little bit further
too. But my name is Splattercat. I sip
through the pile to find what's
worthwhile in the world of indie games
every single day so that you don't have
to. Today I'm on the chopping block. We
were fooling around with Romestead.
Tomorrow will be something else. I look
forward to this game's 1.0. This is that
depressing period now where I really
like an early access game, but I don't
want to play through to the end of the
content and then just sit there
twiddling my thumbs waiting for the 1.0
to come out. So, what I always do right
now is I just shove it completely until
1.0 happens because I have a deep-seated
need to binge. And I felt myself feeling
that with this game, which I think is a
really, really good sign. I'll see y'all
later. Thank you for hanging out. That's
all I got for you folks. Bye.